Simon Flexner Papers 1891-1946 Mss.B.F365
American Philosophical Society
Simon Flexner Papers
1891-1946
Mss.B.F365
American Philosophical Society
115.5 Linear feet
Simon Flexner, born in 1863, one of the nation's leading experts in pathology and bacteriology, was most renowned for his research on cerebrospinal meningitis, polio and infantile paralysis. Arguably though, Flexner's stewardship of the Rockefeller Institute was his greatest contribution to medical and scientific research. His rise in the medical community began in the late nineteenth century in Louisville, Kentucky, where despite not having completed even the seventh grade, Flexner taught himself basic bacteriology by conducting experiments at home using a microscope borrowed from the pharmacy where he served as an apprentice. Granted a medical degree from the University of Louisville School of Medicine in 1889, he went on to a pathology fellowship at the newly opened John Hopkins School of Medicine. Within two short years of leaving Louisville, Flexner received an assistant of pathology appointment at Johns Hopkins. It was a quick ascent and the beginning of a long and brilliant career that included a prestigious appointment at the University of Pennsylvania and then a directorship at the new Rockefeller Institute where he realized his lifelong dream of creating a dynamic and productive research laboratory. The Rockefeller Institute became instantly famous worldwide as the preeminent research facility for virology and under Flexner's direction produced invaluable contributions in pathology, bacteriology, and immunology. This collection does not reflect the early phases of Flexner's career at Johns Hopkins but does document an early interest in meningitis and other infectious diseases with science-related correspondence, laboratory notebooks, and administrative correspondence with the New York City and State Departments of Health. There is abundant material on Flexner's directorship of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, including Flexner's search for staff, an involved process which is detailed in correspondence with the scientists, many of whom became quite famous. Also included is material relating to the other institutions and Rockefeller philanthropies with which Flexner was involved. (Among the most significant correspondence, however, may be that which documents the support of the General Education Board and the Rockefeller Foundation in the development and subsequent reorganization of medical schools following brother Abraham Flexner's scathing report on medical education in the United States and Canada). This collection would be of great interest to anyone interested in the history of bacteriology, histology, and immunology or the general history of modern medicine and philanthropy.
Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946
Bibliography
Flexner, James Thomas, An American Saga, The Story of Helen Thomas and Simon Flexner (Toronto: Little, Brown and Company, 1984). Call no. B F635 a
Flexner, James Thomas, Maverick's Progress, an Autobiography (New York: Fordham University, 1996). Call no. B F635 m
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
Simon Flexner was one of the most influential figures in the life sciences in America, and a prominent member of the scientific establishment that shaped the country's intellectual and social development. Major aspects of this growth are documented in this voluminous collection, which includes correspondence, diaries (circa 1900, 1915-1944), laboratory notebooks (circa 1900-1920), and drafts of articles and addresses.
The early phases of Flexner's academic career -- his medical education at the University of Louisville, his subsequent move to Johns Hopkins (1890-1899), and his tenure at the University of Pennsylvania as professor of pathology (1899-1906) -- are not covered in this collection (however, a number of secondary sources fill these gaps). The entry on Flexner in this note therefore addresses only those files which bear on the intellectual and institutional development of physiology, biochemistry, and biophysics.
Flexner influenced the growth of physiology, biochemistry, and biophysics in two ways: as director of the Rockefeller Institute, and through his positions of leadership in the Rockefeller Foundation, the National Research Council, the Carnegie Foundation and other scientific organizations and journals; his professional papers reflect both aspects of his influence.
Abderhalden, Emil, 1877-1950 ( On physiological and biochemical research in Germany and at the Kaiser-Wilhelm Institute.) Correspondence (5 folders) 1911-1938 German
Adams, Roger, 1889-1971 ( Includes Adams' requests recommendations for Dr. Malcolm Dole for an instructorship in chemistry at University of Illinois, 1929. Correspondence on candidates for Field Secretaryship of Rockefeller Foundation Board in physics, chemistry, and mathematics.) Correspondence (10 items) 1929-1934 English
Alexander, Jerome, b. 1876 ( Correspondence about contributions to Alexander's book on colloid chemistry.) Correspondence (20 items) 1916-1934 English
Alsberg, Carl, 1877-1940 ( Material on USDA Bureau of Chemistry.) Correspondence (15 items) 1913-1920 English
Avery, Oswald Theodore, 1877-1955 ( Informal notice of Flexner's approval of Avery's appointment to the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (RIMR), 1913. General administrative correspondence on the RIMR.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1913-1945 English
Banting, Frederick Grant, Sir, 1891-1941 ( Correspondence concerning production of insulin.) Correspondence (Approximately 50 items) 1923-1937 English
Bergmann, M. (Max), 1886-1944 ( Letters concerning Bergmann's appointment to the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; also scientific and professional correspondence.) Correspondence (35 items) 1933-1942 English
Bohr, Niels, 1885-1962 ( Notice of conference at Institute of Theoretical Physics in Copenhagen on the application of atomic physics to elucidation of fundamental biological problems.) Correspondence (4 items) 1938 English
Cannon, Walter B. (Walter Bradford), 1871-1945 ( Correspondence concerning antivivisection bills of several state legislatures. Letters discussing the work of Wallace O. Fenn and his qualifications to head Division of Physiology at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, should it be revived, 1921.) Correspondence (8 folders) 1910-1938 English
Carnegie Institution of Washington ( Notices of meetings of Trustees; administrative materials relating to meetings, travel, expenses, etc. Letters on funding of a research assistantship for Ulric Nef at Chicago, 1912. Provisional budget for 1915, with appropriations for specific research projects, list of applicants for minor grants, and abstracts of proposals recommended for funding by president of Carnegie Institution, 1915.) Correspondence (4 folders) 1913-1915, 1943 English
Cohn, Edwin J. (Edwin Joseph), 1892-1953 ( Regarding Cohn's liver research. Includes information to Flexner that liver extract had been sent to Janet Vaughan of the Medical Research Council.) Correspondence (5 items) 1919-1927 English
Edsall, David Linn, 1869-1945 ( Includes letters on his acceptance of Chair of Preventive Medicine at Washington University, St. Louis; and giving his reasons for resigning his position at St. Louis; and on acceptance of Chair of Medicine at Harvard. Letter asking Flexner to insure that Cornell consider A. E. Taylor for an opening in physiological chemistry. In the same letter, Edsall describes deficiencies at University of Pennsylvania. Edsall is confident about future of Alfred N. Richards as opportunities for trained pharmacologists are abundant, 3/13/11. In his reply, Flexner expresses doubts on qualifications of Richards as a trained investigator. Correspondence about the first Dunham lecture, 1928.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1910-1930 English
Embree, Edwin Rogers, 1883-1950 ( On the Rockefeller Foundation's support of the life sciences.) Correspondence (24 folders) 1917-1936 English
Fenn, Wallace O. ( Plans for work in biophysics and physiology. Includes Fenn's plans to work with A. V. Hill, William Bayliss, and Sir Frederick Gowland Hopkins in England, 1922. Letter to Flexner outlining offer of professorship of physiology at University of Rochester, 1924.) Correspondence (20 items) 1921-1924 English
Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946. Medical Notebooks ( Records of serum shipped from Flexner's laboratory. Case histories of meningitis and Poliomyelitis victims. Experimental notes of meningitis research.) Notebooks (17 volumes) 1902-1920 English
Heidelberger, Michael ( Includes general correspondence about Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research staff. Correspondence about his visit to Europe, 1924.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1913-1942 English
Johns Hopkins University. School of Hygiene and Public Health ( Reports by William H. Welch and William H. Howell, 1915, and by William H. Welch and Wickliffe Rose on feasibility of establishing an institute or school of hygiene at Johns Hopkins University, submitted to Rockefeller Foundation, 1916. Report on Institute of Hygiene at Johns Hopkins University, 1919 (12 pages). Report of Department of Biometry and Vital Statistics, Johns Hopkins University, 1920. Budget, 1920-1921. Organization chart of Department of Medical Zoology, Johns Hopkins University, 1920-1925.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1916-1925 English
Landsteiner, Karl, 1868-1943 ( Administrative communications.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1914-1937 English
Lecomte du Nouy, Pierre, 1883-1947 ( Includes general correspondence on his work at Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (RIMR), 1921. Report on X-ray crystal analysis and estimates of costs of a complete crystallography department at RIMR, 1926. Letter on Du Nouy's visit to Geophysicial Laboratory of Carnegie Institution to acquire the latest skills in X-ray crystallography. Du Nouy's description of his work at the Institut Pasteur, and information on its internal organization, 1930. Correspondence concerning the supposed accident that BCG vaccine from Institut Pasteur killed children in Lribeck, 1930; Du Nouy's explanation that the deaths could not have been so caused. List of his papers produced at Institut Pasteur, Department of Molecular Physics, 1928-1931.) Correspondence (60 items) 1919-1937 English
Levene, P. A. (Phoebus Aaron), 1869-1940 ( Contain a wealth of information on Levene's laboratory, research reports, and personal and professional correspondence related to Levene's work, as well as to the work of other biochemists. Administrative correspondence about the laboratory at Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (RIMR). Of special interest is the correspondence (July 1, 1933) about nucleic acids research, and about Max Bergmann and general trends in biochemistry. Includes: Letter to Flexner about Casimir Funk's return to work with vitamins, especially chemistry of antiberiberi vitainine, 2/16/20. Letter from Flexner to Levene on latter's chemotherapy research, and Flexner's opinion of Jacobs' research, 3/17/21. Copy of letter from Levene about future organization of chemotherapy research at RIMR. Letter from Flexner about decision of W. J. V. Osterhout to work at RIMR, 10/7/24. Reports of work done in Levene's laboratory, 1925. Letter to Flexner discussing Jacobs' work and need for persons acquainted with methods of microanalysis, 8/8/25. Letter to Flexner on work of Baudisch in photochemistry of pyrimidines, 11/23/25. Letter to Flexner expressing the opinions of work of Bancroft and Rutzler's and Anson and Mirsky's on the reversibility of protein denaturation, 6/10/31. Letter to Flexner explaining he could soon describe in detail pattern of nucleic acid molecules, and outlining work in the physical analysis of these substances in photochemical reactions, 7/1?/33. Letter to Flexner about place of Max Bergmann among contemporary chemists with leanings towards biology, including an expression of views on new trends in biochemistry and those interested in biologically active substances, 11/11/33. Letter to Flexner (not sent) offering to relinquish work on proteins and carbohydrates to accommodate Bergmann, 11/13/33. Correspondence about Bergmann's arrival at RIMR, 1934. Personal correspondence with Flexner in England, 1937-1938. Address given by Flexner at Levene's funeral 9/9/40.) Correspondence (10 folders) 1910-1940 English
Lillie, Frank Rattray, 1870-1947 ( Records related to activities at Woods Hole (1915-1938), material on Lillie's role in the Rockefeller Foundation's program of "experimental biology" (the precursor of "molecular biology"), correspondence related to the National Academy of Sciences, National Research Council, and the Science Advisory Committee (circa 1930s). Letter to Flexner on plans for new laboratory of biochemistry and biophysics at Marine Biological Laboratory, 3/19/21. List of investigators of Marine Biological Laboratory, summer 1923. Letters on appeal to Rockefeller Foundation for funding of research into "vital process" or "experimental biology," 1934. Correspondence about National Academy of Sciences Standing Committee on Funds for Academy Purposes, 1935. Correspondence about nominations to Science Advisory Committee (later, Science Advisory Board) by President Roosevelt, 1935. List of members of the Committee, 1935. Correspondence concerning National Research Council Fellowship Board in Physics, Chemistry, Mathematics and Biology funds to be received from Rockefeller Foundation, 1937-1940. Minutes of Advisory Committee on fellowships of National Research Council, 1/11/36.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1915-1938 English
Loeb, Jacques, 1859-1924 ( Issues related to research problems: Loeb's research, as well as the scientific careers of other workers in the life sciences, for example, Otto Warburg (1915), Samuel Meltzer (1919), and Leonor Michaelis (1924). There is also correspondence related to the Journal of General Physiology. Covers the period of Loeb's tenure at the Rockefeller Institute.) Correspondence (4 folders) 1913-1924 English
Loevenhart, A. S. (Arthur Solomon), 1878-1929 ( Physiology and pharmacology at the University of Wisconsin. Includes scientific correspondence detailing Loevenhart's research on stimulation of respiration in dogs by intravenous injections of sodium cyanide, and published articles on tryparsamide. Draft (written by Loevenhart) of "A Proposed Therapeutic Institute Devoted to Finding Better Methods for Treating the Sick," February 1928 (17 pages). Correspondence on dispute over Loevenhart's supplying tryparsamide to institutions outside of the Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, University of Wisconsin.) Correspondence (45 items) 1910-1929 English
Meyerhof, Otto, 1884-1951 ( Includes correspondence on his visit to the United States, 1923. General correspondence on exchange of reprints.) Correspondence (Approximately 25 items) 1923-1934 English
Michaelis, Leonor, 1875-1949 ( Includes correspondence on his visit to the United States, 1924. Correspondence on arrangements to work at Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (RIMR), 1929. General administrative correspondence concerning RIMR, 1930-1937.) Correspondence (50 items) 1920-1937, 1945 English
Mirsky, Alfred E. ( Scientific and administrative correspondence. Includes correspondence concerning arrangements for him to work at Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1927. Report on his investigation of proteins, especially muscle, 1934.) Correspondence (12 items) 1927-1934, 1944 English
Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945 ( General correspondence. Includes letter to Flexner asking latter's support of Mr. Rosels request to General Education Board for $10,000 for biophysics laboratory at Columbia University, 2/14/28. (Morgan also mentions that Osterhout's work at Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (RIMR) will complement proposed research of Selig Hecht at Columbia University.) Letter to Flexner on distribution of National Research Fund, 4/24/28. Copy of minutes of National Research Fund Board of Trustees meeting, June 1928. Letter from Milliken to Flexner suggesting formation of a subcommittee on physiology of National Research Fund to discuss candidates who should be released from teaching to concentrate on pure research, 6/25/28. Copy of letter of J. J. Abel to National Research Fund on his work on cancer in rats. Letter from John Auer on Wendell H. Griffith's work on internal secretions. List of National Research Fund subcommittees, with names of chairmen and members, 10/10/28. List of applicants to Subcommittee in Pathology and Physiology of National Research Fund, Dec. 1928. Correspondence concerning future of monograph series in experimental biology, edited by Morgan, Jacques Loeb, and W. J. V. Osterhout, 1924. Letter to Flexner on National Research Fund contributions, noting that most of the funds had been collected and suggesting that institutions be surveyed to determine which needed financial support, 5/13/31. Correspondence on Mrs. Kerchoff's endowment, August-December 1933.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1919-1935 English
Murphy, James B. (James Bumgardner), 1884-1950 ( Communications on cancer research and administrative concerns. Includes correspondence on his work on x-ray effects on chicken cancer and on chicken spleen extract to determine origins and development of blood cells. Letter to Flexner on type of organization needed to conduct cancer research; suggests expansion of his laboratory with employment of specialized team of researchers rather than relying on other Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (RIMR) departments, 12/11/27. Administrative correspondence on training of Army Medical Corps doctors, May-July, 1918. Report of his laboratory to RIMR Board of Directors, on X-ray stimulation of lymphocytes and cancer tissues and effects of ultraviolet rays on antigenic property of bacteria, November 1918-January 1919. Letters from Flexner during Murphy's illness February-June, 1920. General administrative correspondence on RIMR. Report of work of Murphy's laboratory of use of X-ray treatment on chronic infections associated with lymphoid overgrowth in tonsils, 10/19/20. Administrative correspondence. Letter to Flexner concerning plans for cancer research program at RIMR, especially need for a first-class physical chemist, 4/8/22. Report on activities of Dr. Mais in his department for 1922-1923. Letters concerning his wish to observe cancer research in England and to visit English supporters of career "germ theory," 1925. General and administrative correspondence. Outline of research in Murphy's laboratory for 1927. Report to Flexner on his visit to Europe, 1927. Correspondence on his work on filterable agent in chicken tumors. Administrative correspondence. Correspondence on his wish to expand cancer research into genetics of cancer. Administrative correspondence, 1933-1939.) Correspondence (10 folders) 1915-1939 English
National Research Council ( Extensive administrative material from the National Research Council. See inventory below for specific information on the materials.) Correspondence (43 folders) 1916-1945 English
Northrop, John Howard, 1891-1987 ( Includes Jacques Loeb's recommendation of Northrop to work at the Institute (1915), Northrop's report on the production of acetone (1918), his work on enzymes (1929), and scientific and administrative communications.) Correspondence (4 folders) 1915-1941 English
Olitsky, Peter K., 1866-1964 ( Work on viruses. Includes correspondence on his work with Dr. Chickering at U. S. Naval Base, Portsmouth, Virginia, on meningitis victims, 1917-1918. Report on meningitis carriers, U. S. Naval Hospital, Portsmouth, Virginia, June-August 1917. Correspondence and reports to Flexner from China when Olitsky was working in outbreaks of meningitis, May-June 1918. Comments by Flexner on some of Olitsky's papers and work with antidysenteric serum and influenza serum. Correspondence on Olitsky's work with plant mosaic virus, successfully cultivated by him in a test tube, March 1925. Correspondence on Olitsky's foot and mouth disease expedition to Europe for U.S.D.A., May 1925-June 1926. Correspondence on Olitsky's work on virus diseases with Florence R. Sabin at Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (RIMR), 1934-1939. General administrative correspondence on RIMR.) Correspondence (7 folders) 1917-1945 English
Osterhout, W. J. V. (Winthrop John Van Leuven), 1871-1964 ( Scientific and administrative material. Includes: General correspondence about Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. Correspondence on his work on bioelectrical phenomena, 1933.) Correspondence (Approximately 40 items) 1927-1941 English
Rivers, Thomas M. (Thomas Milton), 1888-1962 ( Records on Rivers' virus research, and on administrative aspects of his department and the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Hospital. Correspondence on his work with encephalitis and filterable viruses, and their relation to diseases of central nervous system.) Correspondence (4 folders) 1922-1949 English
Rockefeller Foundation ( Minutes of trustees' meetings, 1915. Minutes of Executive Committee meetings, June 1916, 1920. Report of National Committee for Mental Hygiene of work of various agencies involved with mental hygiene, 1914. Plans submitted by William H. Welch and Wickliffe Rose for institute of hygiene, 1915. Report on reorganization of Rockefeller Boards, 5/22/28.) Correspondence (10 folders) 1913-1934 English
Rockefeller Institute ( Administrative materials. Lists of staff members, 1904-1909, 1916-1939. Applications for staff appointments and grants, 1916. Minutes of Board of Scientific Directors, February-April 1914, January 1919. Minutes of Executive Committee, March 1918, February-April 1919.) Correspondence (39 folders) 1914-1946 English
Rockefeller Sanitary Commission ( Includes report on eradication of hookworm disease, 1910.) Records (52 pages) 1910 English
Rose, Wickliffe, 1862-1931 ( Administrative correspondence on work of International Health Board in eradication of diseases, particularly hookworm, yaws, and pellagra in Southern States of United States, yellow fever in South America, and tuberculosis in France in 1917-1918. General and administrative correspondence as director of the International and General Education Boards, concerning funding of research, with list of fellows receiving support in physics, chemistry, mathematics, biology, genetics and plant Datholoor in United States and Europe, October 1926. Plans for administration of fellowships, 1928.) Correspondence (24 folders) 1910-1931 English
Rous, Peyton, 1879-1970 ( Administrative aspects of the Rockefeller Institute, on activities in professional societies, communications related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine, on Flexner's visit to Cambridge and the Cambridge scientific scene (1926-1927), and on tumor virology and protein chemistry.) Correspondence (11 folders) 1916-1941 English
Sabin, Florence Rena, 1871-1953 ( General correspondence, "A Great Anatomist and Educator.") Correspondence (5 folders) 1913-1940 English
Stanley, Wendell M. (Wendell Meredith), 1904-1971 ( Includes general correspondence. Letters to Flexner on his isolation of three types of tobacco mosaic virus, using chemical methods to isolate three different crystalline proteins, and also on his work on inactivation of tobacco mosaic virus through chemical action on the amino groups of the active protein of virus, 4/7, 6/8/36.) Correspondence (18 items) 1935-1941 English